A Guide to the Virginia Constitutional Convention (1829-1830), Records, 1828-1830
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1828-1830
Library of Virginia
35154 and 35181
2.175 cubic feet and one volume
Virginia Constitutional Convention (1829-1830)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1901.
Historical Information
The fact that the state constitution of 1776 had not been voted upon by the general public aroused the strong disapproval of many Virginians, including Thomas Jefferson, who also criticized the inadequate separation of powers and the court system set forth in the document. The more populous counties of western Virginia wanted manhood suffrage, as opposed to freehold suffrage, and also objected to the section of the constitution allowing for only two delegates per county to the General Assembly, regardless of population. Many attempts were made between 1796 and 1827 to call another constitutional convention, but the proposal was always defeated in the General Assembly. As the population in the west increased, though, there was corresponding agitation for a new convention and in 1828 an act was passed in the General Assembly authorizing a popular referendum on the subject. After the voters had approved the measure by a vote of 21,896 to 16,646, an act was passed by the General Assembly on February 10, 1829, to permit the summoning of a convention. Under this act, the people met at their courthouses and elected four members from each of the twenty-four senatorial districts. The act also provided that the constitution should be submitted to the people for ratification or rejection.
The convention met in Richmond on October 5, 1829 and a compromise was made on suffrage and representation issues. It was resolved that there would be thirteen Senators from west of the Blue Ridge and nineteen from east of the Blue Ridge, and that there would be one hundred and twenty-seven members in the House of Delegates - twenty-nine elected from the district west of the Alleghany Mountains; twenty-four from the valley between the Alleghany Mountains and the Blue Ridge Mountains; forty from the Blue Ridge to the head of the tidewater; and thirty-four thence below. The convention did not change the right of suffrage accorded to freeholders, but did extend some rights to reversioners, remaindermen and leaseholders. The convention adjourned on January 15, 1830 and the constitution it drafted was submitted to the voters for approval in April. The constitution was approved and adopted by a vote of 26,055 to 15,563, even though the western counties were far from satisfied with the compromise.
Scope and Content Information
The Virginia Constitutional Convention (1829-1830) records are arranged in two series. Series have been designated for Election Records and Journals.
Series I: Election Records - This series is arranged in three subseries. Subseries have been designated for Convention Election Returns, Election Certificates, Petitions and Memorials and Amendments, and Referendum Election Returns.
Subseries A: Convention Election Returns, 1828 May-July - This subseries contains election returns/poll book tabulations of votes on the question of holding a constitutional convention to amend the state constitution. The records document who voted for and against the proposed convention and also contain a statement of the final tally of votes listed by county.
Subseries B: Election Certificates, Petitions and Memorials, and Amendments, 1829-1830 - The election certificates contain the names of the delegates elected to the convention and the area they represent. The petitions and memorials document attempts, mainly by non-freeholders, to expand suffrage. Lastly, this subseries contains suggested propositions, resolutions and amendments.
Subseries C: Referendum Election Returns, 1830 April-May - This subseries contains poll books, arranged alphabetically by locality, from the referendum for ratifying or rejecting the amended state constitution, enumerating votes for and against the constitution, with a final tally of votes.
Series II: Journal - The Convention Journal (1829 October 5 - 1830 January 15) contains a list of delegates, convention minutes and proceedings of the business conducted each day, and roll call votes on proposed amendments and changes to the state constitution.
Organization
Organized into the following two (2) series: I. Election Records, 1828-1830; II. Journal, 1829-1830.
Contents List
- Series I: Election Records, 1828-1830
  - Subseries A: Convention Election Returns, 1828 May-July
    alphabetical by locality
    - Statement of Vote (see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Poll Books: Accomack County - Buckingham County (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Poll Books: Cabell County - Frederick County (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Poll Books: Giles County - Jefferson County (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Poll Books: Kanawha County - Nansemond County (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Poll Books: Nelson County - Russell County (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poll Books: Scott County - York County (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poll Books: Cities of Norfolk, Petersburg, Richmond and Williamsburg (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Election Certificates, Petitions and Memorials, and Amendments, 1829-1830
    - Election Certificates 1829
      - Election Certificates for Members of the Convention, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Petitions and Memorials 1829-1830
      chronologically
      - Petition of non-freeholders of Richmond City asking for suffrage 1829 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Petition of non-freeholders of Fairfax County desiring suffrage 1829 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Memorial of non-freeholders of Shenandoah County asking for suffrage 1829 October 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Memorial of non-freeholders of Rockingham County asking for suffrage 1829 October 18 and 20 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Memorial of freeholders and non-freeholders of Loudoun County desiring liberalization of constitution 1829 November 16 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Memorial of Nelson County inhabitants requesting change in appointment of magistrates 1829 November 18 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Petition of Alexander Smyth 1830 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Amendments 1829-1830
      - Amendments, Reports and Resolutions, 1829-1830 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries C: Referendum Election Returns, 1830 April-May
    - Poll Books: Accomack County - Botetourt County (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Poll Books: Brooke County - Dinwiddie County (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Poll Books: Elizabeth City County - Grayson County (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Poll Books: Greenbrier County - Henry County (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Poll Books: Isle of Wight County - Lunenburg County (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Poll Books: Madison County - Morgan County (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Poll Books: Nansemond County - Pittsylvania County (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Poll Books: Pocahontas County - Russell County (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poll Books: Scott County - York County (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Oversize - Subseries A: Convention Election Returnss, 1828 May-July
    - Statement of Vote on Holding a Constitutional Convention, 1828 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Journal, 1829-1830, volume
  - Convention Journal, 1829 October 5 - 1830 January 15